Okay so we start today with we are דף פט Daf Peh
Tet 89 and we start with the last line on דף פח
עמוד ב. Daf Peh Chet Amud Bet. And God willing
today we will finish כיסוי הדם. Kisuy HaDam. We end with a
nice bit of אגדתא, Aggadeta, it doubles back for a little bit
of a halachic discussion and then we move on to the next
מצוה Mitzvah relating to eating meat, which is גיד הנשה, Gid HaNasheh,
or prohibition I should say. So ואמר רבא, Ve'amar Rava, last line
on דף פח עמוד ב. Daf Peh Chet Amud Bet. Oh, I
did want to say that yesterday was all about different materials for
כיסוי הדם Kisuy HaDam and we were hard pressed to find exactly
some of the distinctions like between flax seed and flour and so
on. מרדכי Mordechai Harris afterwards mentioned to me, who has been doing
this recently and has some practical experience with it, that yeah, a
couple guys in ישיבה Yeshiva have been learning שחיטה, Shechita, and he
says that he thought that the difference was was that the materials
that you can't do it with either are non-absorbent or are too
absorbent. So even they're like non-absorbent like, you know, metal, or they're
too absorbent like flour and basically just make clumpy flour as opposed
to things that like absorb but, you know, but don't get transformed
in the process. So things like the dirt and things like other
things. I don't know, I've never tried it with the flax seed.
What about the ground rock?
Yeah, I don't know. Anyway, that was his that was his...
the משנה Mishna
says that it's based about whether it can... right, at least that
was the opinion in the משנה, Mishna, that was... who do you
call it, that was רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
it wasn't clear that everybody agreed to that. But yes, that seemed
to be the dominant position in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so now
to continue with some of our אגדתא Aggadeta because we did a
little אגדתא Aggadeta about the אברהם Avraham עפר ואפר Afar VeEfer and
the מצוה Mitzvah of עפר סוטה, Afar Sotah, not the עפר Afar
of כיסוי הדם Kisuy HaDam and the גמרא Gemara explains why, but
I should mention the original locus of this statement of רבא Rava
is in סוטה. Sotah. It's a little ironic for the גמרא Gemara
to quote an אגדתא Aggadeta that is that, you know, only connection
is because it wasn't mentioned in our סוגיא, Sugya, but actually this
originally was mentioned in the context of מסכת סוטה. Masechet Sotah. Let's
just read and then I'll get your question, Charlie. ואמר רבא, Ve'amar
Rava, let's get started, and רבא Rava also
says, בשכר שאמר אברהם אבינו, B'ischar she'amar Avraham Avinu, in this merit
that
אברהם Avraham our father said, אם מחוט ועד שרוך נעל, Im michut
ve'ad seroch naal, if from a leather strap to a to a
shoestrap, I will take from anything that is yours. Right, this is
after he fought the war against the kings and, you know, and
they wanted to offer him, you know, from some of the booty
and he said, no, you know, I don't want you to say
you made me rich, I I won't take anything of yours. So
because he mentioned a leather strap and strings, he probably see where
that's going, זכו בניו לשתי מצוות, Zachu banav lishtei mitzvot, his children
inherited two מצוות: Mitzvot: חוט של תכלת, Chut shel techeilet, the string
of תכלת, Techeilet, that's the string, the like the shoestrap is like
a string; ורצועה של תפילין, Veretzuah shel tefillin, and the strap of
תפילין, Tefillin, that's the strap. So he merit those two מצוות. Mitzvot.
So now if we speak in the context of what the גמרא
Gemara said before, that we're not just mentioning any מצוות, Mitzvot, but
מצוה Mitzvah in which a person derives some real benefit from in
this world. So how does this work? בשלמא רצועה של תפילין, Bishelama
retzuah shel tefillin, I understand the strap of תפילין, Tefillin, דכתיב, Dichtiv,
the verse says, וראו כל עמי הארץ כי שם ה' נקרא עליך,
V'ra'u kol amei ha'aretz ki shem Hashem nikra alecha, all the nations
of the world will see that the name of God has been
called upon you, ותניא רבי אליעזר הגדול אומר, V'tanya Rabbi Eliezer HaGadol
omer, we taught that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer the Great said, אלו
תפילין שבראש, Eilu tefillin shebarosh, this is seeing the the name of
God, so תפילין Tefillin has the name of God, also has a
שין Shin and a דלת Dalet on the outside, a שין Shin
on the בית Bayit and a דלת Dalet on the, you know,
in the קשר, Kesher, so they see that the name of God
has called upon you and in the end of the verse is
ויראו ממך, V'yaru mimka, they're fearful of you. So that's the benefit
you have, that because you have the תפילין, Tefillin, everybody is afraid
of you, you know, you're you have the awe of of the
other people, the your awe is on other people is on the
other nations. אלא חוט של תכלת מאי, Ela chut shel techeilet mai,
what is the benefit, this is the way רש"י Rashi reads this,
what's the benefit of the string of תפילין, Tefillin, of the string
of ציצית, Tzitzit, the blue string of ציצית? Tzitzit? Where's the practical
benefit in this world? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita,
רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, מה
נשתנה תכלת מכל כל הצבעונים, Ma nishtana techeilet mikol kol hatzivonim, in
what way was תכלת, Techeilet, why was תכלת Techeilet chosen over all
over other colors to be on the תפילין? Tefillin?
ציצית, Tzitzit, excuse me. מפני שתכלת דומה לים, Mipnei shetecheilet domeh le'yam,
because the תכלת Techeilet is similar to the ocean,
וים דומה לרקיע, V'yam domeh l'rakia, the ocean's color is similar to
the heavens,
ורקיע דומה לאבן ספיר, V'rakia domeh l'even sapir, and the heaven color
is similar to the color of sapphire, ואבן ספיר דומה לכסא הכבוד,
V'even sapir domeh lekisei hakavod, and the sapphire color is similar to
the very color of God's heavenly throne. דכתיב, Dichtiv, it says, ויראו
את אלוהי ישראל, Vayiru et elohei Yisrael, they saw the God of
Israel, ותחת רגליו כמעשה לבנת הספיר, Vetachat raglav kema'aseh livnat hasapir, underneath
His legs was like the
was like the making of the sapphire stone, וכעצם השמים לטוהר, Uche'etzem
hashamayim latohar, and like the color of the heavens, which shows that
heavens is like sapphire, and sapphire is the where at least God's
feet were in this image, and how does that get to the
כסא הכבוד? Kisei HaKavod? Because דכתיב, Dichtiv, you might have assumed that
it's the same thing as the footstool, but even yet another verse
says, דכתיב, Dichtiv, כמראה אבן ספיר דמות
כסא, K'mareh even sapir dmut kisei, the appearance of the sapphire stone
is the appearance of the heavenly throne. So, how does that explain
what... the benefit is? So רש״י Rashi says well if it's the
color if it's the color of God's throne then it means that
when God is constantly on His throne He's always remembering the merit
of ציצית tzitzis so some merit merit will accrue to us, which
is interesting. The the other way of saying it, the more obvious
way, although it doesn't really explain the question about where do we
get practical benefit, although it's not really clear that's the question the
גמרא Gemara is asking, is that you know that we by this
we remember God or we have a connection to God. So that
really does tie into they see that the name of God is
called upon you. So maybe the emphasis here not like רש״י's Rashi
how do we get some practical benefit in this world, but in
what way are these מצוות mitzvos in particular מצוות mitzvos that are
like particularly meaningful. I mean there's a lot of מצוות, mitzvos, why
pick these? So whereas before there was an emphasis on like we
accrued some practical benefit, here maybe the emphasis is on is you
know that strong connection to God. And certainly one of the themes
of אברהם Avraham is you know is the whole the ברית bris
and you know and and and you know and I will be
for you הלך לפני והיה תמים hilech lefanai veheyeh tamim ונתתי ביני
ובינך venasasi beini ubeinecha what is it? No,
but it's also but there's another פסוק pasuk about
there's a פסוק pasuk about
there's a פסוק pasuk that I will be your God, I'm sorry
I can't believe I can't remember that פסוק. pasuk. Anyway, so the
emphasis of the you know the the intimate relationship of God and
of God and אברהם Avraham and that sense of connection, you know,
to me that's sort of a little bit more obviously what the
גמרא Gemara here is getting at. Yes.
Two things, one is I'm surprised they don't mention that the לוחות
luchos were made of sapphire.
According to a מדרש. Medrash.
Yeah, okay. Okay, that's interesting.
Yeah, second thing, this is awfully anthropomorphic.
Oh yeah. Well there are look there are look alright
like something of God on you.
Yeah. I mean look there are anthropomorphic statements in the in the
תורה, Torah, you know, what are you going to do with that?
I mean the fact is that the גמרא Gemara isn't recoiling from
it, isn't avoiding them. Yeah. Yeah, that's true.
But the fact and but it's also besides that it's a little
pagan, we can't have an image of God but you can wear
a little piece
that reminds you God is this color. Right. Right. Exactly. What is
God's color what what is God's favorite color right?
Reminds
reminds me of Christian
relics.
Yeah, alright it's not going that far but it is true, it
is true that there is some anthropomorphism in the תורה, Torah, alright
I alright anyway I do think that here it's easier to read
this as speaking about something that has the power is is that
it speaks to that direct connection we have with God, God's name
is upon us, God the color of God's כיסא kisei is upon
us, that certainly seems to be more of the direct connection here
than the question of practical benefit. Okay, Mike you wanted to say
something?
No no I just wanted to get yeah best back to what
you're saying. So when the גמרא Gemara is saying they say תפילין
tfillin they're saying בשלמא. bishlama. So what בשלמא bishlama would so in
your you're saying that the בשלמא bishlama means that
like I understand why the where the benefit of תפילין tfillin comes
from but you know what the power of תפילין tfillin is, why
particularly that מצווה. mitzvah. But what so then but
why but it's needs to me that it's they're trying to go
for practical benefit because they could have picked a lot of other
things. They could say you know but you could be close to
God as opposed to saying that then the nations...
No not a lot of practical things fit into the חוט chut
and the שרוך נעל. sroch naal. So but again the point is
like what makes these
special? So רש״י's Rashi saying what makes them special that there's practical
benefit, but I don't think that's the only way of saying what
makes them special. Meaning we're already we're already limited to saying the
תפילין tfillin and ציצית tzitzis because of the פסוק, pasuk, but now
the question is okay but within the context of this מדרש Midrash
you know and yes we get the connection but why you know
what's so special about these more than other things. Anyway that's the
way I read it. רש״י Rashi reads it where's the practical benefit.
Okay, רב גבעון. Reb Givan.
Okay
where are we? Okay. אמר רבי אבא Amar Rabbi Abba so רבי
אבא Rabbi Abba says קשה גזל הנאכל kashah gezel hanachal גזל gezel
the food that excuse me thing that you steal that you then
consume, meaning so stolen product you know it's if you steal something
and it's still around okay you make restitution. But if you steal
something and you literally eaten it or you've used it and now
it's not around anymore and now you're feeling guilty and oh my
god now I'm going to have to return it but I've already
stolen millions of dollars and where am I you know it's all
the money's been spent where am I going to get that money?
So that is very very difficult to have the to find the
ability to return that, you know, the the strength of character and
will or whatever to be able to return it after it's been
already you know used up. שאפילו צדיקים גמורים אין יכולים להחזירה. she'afillu
tzadikim gemurim ein yaholim lehachazirah.
Even the most righteous of of people are not able always to
make restitution, either that they don't have the money or it's also
a challenge to to make restitution after it's been you know even
if even once you don't have the object itself that you can
just give back. שנאמר shene'emar as the verse says בלעדי רק אשר
אכלו הנערים. biladai rak asher achlu hane'arim.
When אברהם Avraham says I'm not going to take anything he says
oh the one thing is what the lads you know what my
retinue ate you know from when we were going out to war
that you know that we're going to keep. So basically here it
was that it was whatever the booty or whatever, they took some
of the stuff for themselves and אברהם Avram is now saying I'm
going to make you good on that. Now of course simple sense
of the verse is like that they're entitled to. Right. They're running
out and they're fighting the war or whatever, they're entitled to at
least that portion of the booty whatever, but then about becoming rich,
it's almost like sense of wages. But here it's saying that no,
if אברהם Avram was saying he wasn't entitled to it, it's actually
pretty harsh language he uses, because it's considered like גזל. gezel. You
know, here it's the booty that they capture, you know, you think
well the rules of warfare entitled them to that, but no, maybe
because it had to be offered to אברהם, Avram, it shows that
he wasn't entitled and therefore it was something that was stolen, he
didn't steal it but at least his retinue stole it, and אברהם
Avraham has to say that we're going to have to allow to
just let go, that I'm not going to be able to return.
Okay.
Does it actually really say it was גזל? gezel?
Well, not by אברהם, Avraham, but by his retinue, apparently,
that's the way it's sort of framing it. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן
משום רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Amar Rabi Yochanan mishum Rabi Elazar berabi
Shimon, רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan said in the name of רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון, Rabi Elazar berabi Shimon, כל מקום שאתה מוצא דבריו של
רבי אלעזר בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי בהגדה, kol makom she'ata motzei
d'varav shel Rabi Elazar beno shel Rabi Yose HaGelili b'Hagada, any time
you find the words of רבי אלעזר Rabi Elazar the son of
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabi Yose HaGelili in הגדה, Hagada, עשה אזנך כאפרכסת,
asay oznecha ke'arparcheset, make your ear like a אפרכסת, arparcheset,
which is some type of a like a sieve or a box
in which they would throw like the wheat that you would process
in a mill, so you basically you just, you know, it would
be a big collecting bin and you throw everything in it in
order to really to hear like everything that he has to say.
Now where is he saying something?
Is it רבי אלעזר הגדול? Rabi Elazar Hagadol?
I was wondering if that was רבי אלעזר הגדול. Rabi Elazar Hagadol.
I meant to look at it. See, but where's the רבי, where's
the רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון?
So anyway, I think, I think it's actually the next דרשה drasha
that he's about to quote. Okay, so presumably this is the דרשה
drasha that we are saying in his name. לא מרבכם מכל העמים
חשק ה' בכם, Lo merubchem kol ha'amim chashak Hashem bachem,
not because you are greater than all the other nations God has
desired you. So but because rather you are smaller than the other
nations, at the end of the verse is, but it's rather because
of the oath that God has made to your fathers. Okay, so
the emphasis, the real point of the verse is God desires you
not because you are physically great and large but because he has
an, but because of the relationship and because of the ברית. brit.
But now here's the going to be the דרשה. drasha. אמר להם
הקדוש ברוך הוא לישראל, Amar lahem HaKadosh Baruch Hu l'Yisrael, God said
to ישראל, Israel, חשקני בכם, chashkani bachem,
I desire you, חשק ה' בכם, chashak Hashem bachem, right, I desire
you, שאפילו בשעה שאני משפיע לכם גדולה, she'afilu besha'ah she'ani maspia lachem
gedola, why do I desire you? Here's why I desire you. שאפילו
בשעה שאני משפיע לכם גדולה, she'afilu besha'ah she'ani maspia lachem gedola, even
when I give you greatness, אתם ממעטים עצמכם לפני, atem mamitim atzmechem
lefanai, you make yourselves small. So the way read the way the
way the verse reads is לא מרבכם חשק ה' בכם ויבחר בכם,
lo merubchem chashak Hashem bachem vayivchar bachem,
not because you are great or not because or because rather you
don't make yourself great, כי אתם המעט מכל העמים, ki atem hame'at
mikol ha'amim, you make yourself small, meaning even when you get greatness
you deal with it humbly and you don't treat yourself like big
shots, you treat yourself, you know, you
as small, not in a belittling sense but you know you make
yourself as humble. Where do you know this? אתם ממעטים עצמכם לפני,
atem mamitim atzmechem lefanai, נתתי גדולה לאברהם, nasati gedola l'Avraham, I gave
greatness to אברהם, Avraham, ואמר לפני, ve'amar lefanai, and he said before
me, ואנכי עפר ואפר, ve'anochi afar va'efer, I am dust and ashes.
That's the tie in to the עפר ואפר afar va'efer discussion. למשה
ולאהרן, L'Moshe ve'Aharon, I gave greatness to משה Moshe and אהרן, Aharon,
right, I made them the high priest and the, you know, the
ruler, ואמרו, ve'amru,
they said, ונחנו מה, venachnu mah, what are we? We're nothing. Right,
לא עלינו lo aleinu but that was they were sort of trying
to tell בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael don't complain to us. Okay. לדוד
אמר, L'David amar, to דוד David
I gave greatness to דוד David and what did he say? ואנכי
תולעת ולא איש, ve'anochi tola'at velo ish, I am a worm and
not a man. I'm you know a humble per- I'm so humble
or I'm so nothing. He was expressing his humility by saying he
was nothing. אבל עובדי כוכבים אינו כן, Aval ovdei kochavim eino ken,
but the idolaters this is not the case. נתתי גדולה לנמרד, Nasati
gedola l'Nimrod, I gave greatness to נמרד, Nimrod, אמר amar he said,
הבה נבנה לנו עיר, hava nivneh lanu ir, let's go they, you
know, according to the חז"ל, Chazal, נמרד Nimrod was in charge of
the מגדל בבל, Migdal Bavel, let's build a tower and reach the
heaven, so he thought he would compete with me, you give them
greatness and now they think they're in my league and they're going
to compete with me. לפרעה, L'Paroh, I gave greatness to פרעה, Paroh,
אמר amar what did he say? מי ה', Mi Hashem,
who is God that I should listen to him? Completely rejected me.
לסנחריב, L'Sancheriv, to סנחריב, Sancheriv, אמר amar he said, מי בכל אלהי
הארצות, mi bechol elohei artzot, who of all the gods of the
lands have stood against me? Right, so he's greater than all the
gods of all of the lands including God. לנבוכדנצר, L'Nevuchadnezzar, I gave
greatness to נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar, אמר amar אעלה על במתי עב, e'eleh bamatei
av,
I will go up on a cloud, on a high cloud, you
know, basically I will dwell upon high. ולחירם מלך צור, U'leChiram melech
Tzor, and to חירם Chiram the king of צור, Tzor, אמר amar
and what did he say? This is the one that שלמה Shlomo
you know sort of collaborated with in the building of the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash and he said מושב אלהים ישבתי בלב ימים, moshav
elohim yashavti belev yamim, I have
the dwelling of God, I have dwelt in the heart of the
of the oceans. So you see that they, you give them a
little greatness and they think they're as great as I am whereas
by the great ones amongst the Jewish people I give them greatness
and they speak about how humble they are in my presence, how
nothing they are in my presence. It reminds me of
this routine that Bill Cosby had where he talked about
the creation of the world and the creation of woman or whatever
and he says and God made the world and it and God
the first day and it was good and God the second day
and it was
good he says and
So anyway. All right, anyway. So all right, anyway.
So that is
the tie-in here, עפר ואפר, Afar Va'efer, about how humbly they take
their greatness. ואמר, Ve'amar,
okay, where are we?
ואמר רבא ואיתימא רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar Rava Ve'iteima Rabi Yochanan, so Rava
said, some say Rabbi Yochanan said, גדול שנאמר במשה ואהרן יותר משנאמר
באברהם, Gadol shene'emar beMoshe veAharon yoter mishene'emar beAvraham, it’s all a little
ironic, greater is what it says by Moshe and Aaron than what
it says by Abraham. It really means more humble. It’s great in
how humble it is, okay? דאילו באברהם כתיב, De'ilu beAvraham ketiv, by
Abraham it
says, ואנכי עפר ואפר, Ve'anochi afar va'efer, I am dust and ashes,
which is at least something. It’s dust and ashes. ואילו במשה ואהרן
כתיב, Ve'ilu beMoshe veAharon ketiv, by Moshe and Aaron it says, ונחנו
מה, Venachnu mah, what are we? We're nothing.
What are we? We're nothing. So nothing is obviously less than dust
and ashes. Okay. ואמר רבא ואיתימא רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar Rava Ve'iteima Rabi
Yochanan, אין העולם מתקיים אלא בשביל משה ואהרן. Ein ha'olam mitkayem ela
bishvil Moshe veAharon. The world only exists because of Moshe and Aaron.
Here we mean because of the humility, well, it’s a question about
whether we mean that. Let’s see what the proof is. כתיב הכא,
Ketiv hacha, it says here, ונחנו מה, Venachnu mah, what are we?
We're nothing. וכתיב התם, Uchetiv hatam, it says over there, תולה ארץ
על בלימה, Toleh eretz al belimah, that God suspends the world on
a little like a peg or something, but בלי מה Beli mah
is like on nothing, בלי Beli without מה Mah without anything. So
they said we're nothing, and here it says the whole world is
suspending on their nothingness, on their nothing, on the nothing of Moshe
and Aaron. So it could mean, I would think in the theme
of this, what it means is because of the merit of their
humility, the world is surviving. It's not necessarily saying that, it could
just be a nice little גזירה שוה Gezeirah shavah connecting the words,
but it's actually saying on the merit of everything that they did,
not just focusing on the merit of their humility.
Since it happens to pass their lifetime? What? Since it happens to
pass their lifetime, otherwise they're not around anymore.
Well, right, exactly. Their merit continues to sustain the world.
But we don't usually invoke like that. We do Rosh Hashanah, זכות
אבות. Zechut avot. We don't do זכות משה ואהרן. Zechut Moshe veAharon.
Well, the idea of זכות אבות, Zechut avot, it’s an interesting point.
There is a very different tone to the sense of the זכות
הצדיקים Zechut hatzadikim to the sense of זכות אבות. Zechut avot. זכות
אבות Zechut avot really speaks much more towards the whole relationship and
the ברית Brit and so on. And God is always saying, זכרתי
את בריתי, Zacharti et briti, זכרתי את בריתי, Zacharti et briti, and
so on. The idea of the merit of צדיקים, Tzadikim,
you’re right, is
more sort of like if you would a bank account, that because
of this merit, the future
generations inherit, reap the interest off of that, or reap the benefit.
But it’s conceptually very different than the זכות אבות. Zechut avot. זכות
אבות Zechut avot really speaks to the foundation of the ברית Brit
and the relationship with God and so on. It’s also very much
ברית אבות Brit avot and זכות אבות Zechut avot are intertwined concepts.
But you are right in general, it’s not so often that we
talk about the זכות Zechut of other than זכות אבות, Zechut avot,
we don't really talk not just Moshe and Aaron, there's a general
concept of the זכות Zechut of the צדיקים, Tzadikim, although it is
a concept in the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay. So now we go on. אמר רבי אילא, Amar
Rabi Ila, אין העולם מתקיים אלא במי, Ein ha'olam mitkayem ela bemi,
now that we're talking about the importance of humility, we're going to
go to other important sort of features. I should mention since we
are talking about the issue of humility, and to the point where
the גמרא Gemara even goes so far as to say, oh, ha,
it’s sort of like saying what is that famous joke, I'm sure
everybody's heard such an old chestnut about נוורדוק. Novardok. נוורדוק Novardok was
into this מוסר Mussar about
how putting themselves down and how nothing man is and we have
to be so humble. So the מוסר זאגער, Mussar sager, as every
day they would sit in the ישיבה Yeshiva and they'd say, איך
בין גארנישט, Ich bin gornisht, איך בין גארנישט, Ich bin gornisht, and
they do that, I'm nothing, they do it over and over for
like a half hour. So some guy walks in off the street
and he’s never seen this before, he doesn't know what's going on.
Everybody's sitting around going איך בין גארנישט. Ich bin gornisht. He says,
all right, when in Rome. So he sits down at the table
and starts doing the same thing, איך בין גארנישט, Ich bin gornisht,
איך בין גארנישט. Ich bin gornisht. So the guy next to him
says, who is this joker walks off the street and
thinks he’s גארנישט? Gornisht? So that’s like, who is this, Abraham thinks
he’s עפר ואפר? Afar va'efer? Anyway,
and the עפר ואפר, Afar va'efer, that’s a
מדרגה. Madreiga. Anyway, but it is a little extreme, right? That the
גמרא Gemara is sort of making
this point that, oh, עפר ואפר Afar va'efer already, Moshe and Aaron
didn't even consider themselves to עפר ואפר. Afar va'efer. So it does
seem like an extreme that we're not used to in terms of
this issue of humility. And it's worth pointing that out, which is
that quite interestingly,
רמב"ם, Rambam, who very much in his הלכות דעות Hilchos Deos and
in
his discussion about his הקדמה Hakdamah to פרקי אבות Pirkei Avos and
so on, is obviously very influenced by Aristotle's Nicomachean Ethics in terms
of character traits and the golden mean and the balance between extremes
and so on. When it comes to the issue of humility, he
takes
strong issue with the Greek approach, because the Greeks actually did
not... whereas the רמב"ם Rambam even didn't even talk about like a
mean like golden mean when it came to humility and pride, he
said you need to go to the opposite extreme, you need to
be super, super humble, you know, and spoke about the principle of
מאד מאד הוי שפל רוח me'od me'od hevei shefal ruach
and went on and on about, you know, he has these like
very graphic discussions in his פירוש המשניות Perush HaMishnayot about how, sort
of, you know, how humble you have to be. So, you know,
it is interesting that that is not
a character trait, a value so much in the Western society, the
value of humility. And it is a very important sort of like
religious value, which again does not mean that you are not honest
with yourself and your accomplishments. You know, if משה ענו מכל אדם,
Moshe anav mikol adam, it doesn't mean that he denied everything that
he accomplished and so on. And there's the famous גמרא Gemara at
the end of סוטה Sotah which says, you know,
משמת רבי בטלה ענווה מן העולם, mishemat Rabbi batla anavah min ha'olam,
and somebody said והאיכא אנא, ve'ika ana, what do you mean there's
no humble people around? I'm still here.
So, but humility has a lot to do with what we have
here, you know, with אנכי עפר ואפר, anochi afar va'efer, sort of
your standing vis-a-vis God and not attributing stuff to yourself and not
sort of seeing yourself as the most, as the center of attention.
And you know, there's a lot of other things about humility which
is not pretending you, you know, you didn't accomplish things but acknowledging
what that means given with the talents that God has given you
and you know, given your relationship to other people and so on.
Anyway, so it is worth pointing out that the גמרא Gemara is,
it does seem a little bit extreme. Oh, you know, משה Moshe
and אהרן Aharon are not, you know, are, you know, you know,
אברהם Avraham was calling himself עפר ואפר, afar va'efer, משה Moshe and
אהרן Aharon didn't want better, but it points to the importance of,
I think, you know, of humility which we're not so, you know,
which again is not so much of a Western value. You wanted
to say something, Charlie? Okay, so let's continue this now. אמר רבא
ואיתימא רבי יוחנן, Amar Rava ve'itayma Rabbi Yochanan, and רבא Rava said
and some say רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, אין העולם מתקיים אלא
בשביל משה ואהרן. ein ha'olam mitkayem ela bishvil Moshe veAharon. Oh, I
did that one. No, I did that one. Okay, אמר רבי אילעא,
Amar Rabbi Ila'a,
first wide line, אין העולם מתקיים אלא בשביל מי שבולם את עצמו
בשעת מריבה. ein ha'olam mitkayem ela bishvil mi shebolem et atzmo bish'at
merivah.
The world only is sustained by me, someone that keeps his mouth
shut at a time of fighting, you know, don't give that angry
retort back, let people say mean things and don't respond back, you'll
just fuel the flames and so on. שנאמר, shene'emar, בולם bolem is
to like close your mouth. שנאמר, shene'emar, as the verse says, I
don't know, but that's how it's used. Okay, שנאמר shene'emar as the
verse says תולה ארץ על בלימה, toleh eretz al belimah, the world
is sustained on בלימה, belimah, which we're now learning to mean is
בולם, bolem, on the one who silences himself. רבי אבהו אמר, Rabbi
Abbahu amar, רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu says מי שמשים עצמו כמי שאינו,
mi shemesim atzmo k'mi she'eino,
the world is sustained by one who makes himself like he is,
does not exist. Again, so these are all related to the humility
idea, right? Because if you're willing to be in a fight and
somebody says mean things and not respond, it's like it's not all
about your pride is at stake and you have to respond back
or whatever, the value of peace and of not feeding into the
argument is more important than your, you know, injured pride and your
being offended. So similarly now it says the world is only on
those that make themselves as if they don't exist, שנאמר shene'emar as
the verse says ומתחת זרועות עולם, umitachat zero'ot olam, under the, you
know, again, it's a poetic verse we're coming up to actually, under
the arms of the world, which is reading ומתחת, umitachat, those that
make themselves as if they are underneath, that let people, you know,
basically let people walk on them, they are זרועות עולם, zero'ot olam,
they are the support of the world. אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi
Yitzchak, said רבי יצחק, Rabbi Yitzchak, מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv, what is
meant by the verse האמנם אלם צדק תדברון מישרים תשפטו בני אדם?
ha'umnam elem tzedek tedaberun mesharim tishpetu b'nei adam? Is it in truth
will the
silent, will the mute person speak righteousness, מישרים תשפטו בני אדם mesharim
tishpetu b'nei adam with just laws judge the people. So we're going
to make a דרשה drasha on that. מה אומנותו של אדם, Ma
umanuto shel adam, האמנם ha'umnam rather than reading in truth but reading
אומנות, umanut, what is the אומנות, umanut, what is the livelihood or
the primary endeavor of a person בעולם ba'olam in this
world, ישים עצמו כאלם. yasim atzmo k'elem. What? בעולם הזה ba'olam hazeh
in this world, ישים עצמו כאלם, yasim atzmo k'elem, should make himself
like somebody that is
mute, he should האמנם אלם, ha'umnam elem, be silent, don't get into
fights, don't respond, okay, you know, that's what you should work on
in this world. יכול אף לדברי תורה, Yachol af ledivrei Torah, maybe
you should be silent even when it comes to דברי תורה divrei
Torah matters, and maybe in the context of responding to fights, maybe
this even means, you know, maybe you shouldn't defend תורה. Torah. תלמוד
לומר כתיב צדק תדברון, Talmud lomar ktiv tzedek tedaberun, you should speak
justice, and the תורה Torah is called צדק, tzedek, and so therefore
that is something you have to speak up about. יכול יגיס דעתו,
Yachol yagis da'ato, maybe you can feel like arrogant if let's say
you came to defend תורה Torah and you, you know, won a
fight, somebody was challenging תורה Torah and you came to defend, you
know, you know, the, you know, the honor of תורה, Torah, maybe
now you should feel, you know, you should feel haughty or self-satisfied.
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse says מישרים תשפטו בני אדם, mesharim
tishpetu b'nei adam, and so what does this mean? So מישרים mesharim
comes from the word of just laws but from the word of
מישור, mishor, same word, it means flat or straight, so רש"י Rashi
says like a valley. You should make yourself like a valley, you
should lower yourself even if you have to come and speak about
תורה Torah and defend the honor of תורה. Torah. that does not
mean that you should sort of be very sanctimonious about it or
self-satisfied. אמר רבי זירא ואי תימא רבה בר ירמיה. Amar Rabbi Zeira
ve-isima Rabba bar Yirmia. Okay, so that was a nice little aggadic
digression and now back back to business. So says רבי זירא Rabbi
Zeira and some say רבה בר ירמיה Rabba bar Yirmia says, מכסין
בעפר עיר הנדחת. mechasin be-afar Ir Ha-nidachat. You can use the dust
of an עיר הנדחת, Ir Ha-nidachat, a city that had committed idolatry
and you destroyed the whole city and burnt the whole city, you
can use the dust of that city for a פרה אדומה Parah
Adumah for for כיסוי הדם. Kisuy Ha-dam. So now obviously it's dust,
it's dust or ashes or whatever you burnt it, but the problem
is that things in an עיר הנדחת Ir Ha-nidachat you can't derive
benefit from. מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו, mitzvot lav le-henot nitnu, so that's
our conversation. Okay, ואמאי, ve-amai, why is it true? איסורי הנאה isurei
hana'ah הוא, hu, it's forbidden in benefit. And here we're assuming you
can't use things that are forbidden in benefit even to do a
מצווה. mitzvah. So אמר זירי, amar Ziri, לא נצרכא אלא עפר עפרה.
lo nitzrecha ela afar afarah. We don't mean the ashes of a
because we just got through having a whole discussion that עפר afar
and אפר efer sometimes are used interchangeably. So first if זירי Ziri
says the עפר afar of an עיר הנדחת, Ir Ha-nidachat, you assume
what they mean is the אפר efer of an עיר הנדחת, Ir
Ha-nidachat, the ashes of things that have been burnt. He says, no
no no, you misunderstood. We're not talking about the ashes of things
you burnt. We're talking about the dust of the עיר הנדחת. Ir
Ha-nidachat. You go to an עיר הנדחת Ir Ha-nidachat and you take
some of its dirt. Okay, now why is that okay? Maybe that
should also be forbidden, the dirt? So it says first of all,
right, דכתיב, de-ketiv, the verse says ואת כל שללה תקבץ אל תוך
רחובה, ve-et kol shelalah tikbot el toch rechovah, gather all of its
booty into this city into the center of the of the square,
ושרפת, ve-sarafta,
and burn. מי שאינו מחוסר אלא קביצה ושרפה, mi she-eino mechusar ela
kevitzah u-sereifah, something that all you have to do is gather it
and burn it, יצא זה שמחוסר תלישה קביצה ושרפה, yatza zeh she-mechusar
telishah kevitzah u-sereifah,
which excludes this, which you have to uproot, you'd have to, if
you wanted to burn the soil, you'd have to dig the soil
up and burn it. And also like as Michael said, you really
think that the entire dirt will now be forever forbidden? Normally we
say that things that are connected to the ground can't be forbidden,
if you worship the ground as עבודה זרה avodah zarah it doesn't
become forbidden, although the Torah does say והיתה תל עולם לא תבנה,
ve-hayetah tel olam lo tibaneh, don't rebuild the city, but it doesn't
say you can't plant on the ground or something. So anyway, but
that's one approach גמרא Gemara takes. But it also just says here
that you don't burn and it doesn't become forbidden things that have
to be basically torn out or ripped out of the ground. They're
not basically moveable. Which raises interesting questions about what about the homes?
Right. What about the
crops?
Right. Basically, for whatever reason, you have a clump that they started
digging up and it's loose, you couldn't use that.
Presumably that would be correct, if you had loose dirt that would
be. Okay, so anyway, so we could discuss that more when we
learn סנהדרין Sanhedrin and עיר הנדחת, Ir Ha-nidachat, come back in six
years. אלא, ela, so anyway, יצא זה שמחוסר תלישה קביצה ושרפה. yatza
zeh she-mechusar telishah kevitzah u-sereifah. So it doesn't apply to the dirt
of the עיר הנדחת. Ir Ha-nidachat. So therefore you are allowed to
cover with it. ורבא אמר, ve-Rava amar, that was his answer. We're
not talking about ashes, we're talking about dirt. Dirt isn't forbidden. ואמר
רבא, ve-amar Rava, רבא Rava says
no, we're talking about ashes! Even so, מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו, mitzvot
lav le-henot nitnu, מצוות mitzvot are not for getting benefit from, meaning
that the reward, the benefit you get for doing a מצווה mitzvah
is not a physical benefit. Now, you could read that as an
important like metaphysical
statement, you're not, we're not supposed to acknowledge any benefit from מצוות
mitzvot in the doing of the מצווה mitzvah and then or maybe
somehow the מצווה mitzvah benefit overshadows, but it more simply is not
a statement about מצוות, mitzvot, but a statement about the nature of
איסורי הנאה. isurei hana'ah. That איסורי הנאה, isurei hana'ah, what does it
mean that you can't get benefit from
something? It means a type of physical real-world benefit, it does not
mean a religious spiritual benefit. For example, there are things that are
not physical as well. Let's say an intellectual benefit. Can I, here's
a whole question, can I study a cadaver in order to learn
something, scientific knowledge? Or is that deriving benefit from a מת? met?
And generally, the general answer is that's not, assuming you're not a
כהן, kohen, that's not deriving benefit from a מת, met, because that's
not considered benefit. Benefit is more monetary or physical. Intellectual benefit isn't
benefit. So similar religious benefit, spiritual, getting credit for a מצווה mitzvah
does not count as forbidden benefit by איסורי הנאה isurei hana'ah and
therefore yes you can use the ashes for covering for כיסוי הדם.
Kisuy Ha-dam. Yes.
There are a couple מצוות mitzvot that the Torah explicitly lists some
benefit.
Like like what we said before, like להוציא צדקה le-hotzi tzedakah or
these types of things, הארכת ימים. ha-rachtei yamim. Yeah, but again all
of that is first of all it's derivative, it's not direct, and
second of all, I mean that's the basic point, it's derivative. If
I go ahead and I study a cadaver and because of that
I'm able to pass my medical exam and become a doctor
and make a nice living, so it's benefit that derived, but in
the actual direct encounter with the cadaver, my direct benefit there was
my intellectual knowledge. So here too my direct benefit is fulfilling the
מצווה mitzvah and that doesn't count.
Don't we acknowledge pleasure as a benefit though?
Yes, but what type of pleasure? Physical pleasure. For example, there's a
whole discussion about music. Things that are אסור בהנאה, assur be-hana'ah, like
music is not not biblical
that type of
pleasure.
You mean like the שופר גזול shofar gazul that we're talking about?
Like if I listen to a שופר גזול? shofar gazul?
Right, so there's questions about that although that's also a question about
using something. You're using the שופר shofar as opposed to just hearing
the sound. So there it's a little different because you're actually like
using it.
Anyway, feel good about doing something that's a מצוה mitzvah to say
you shouldn't do it.
That is not the type of benefit that we're talking about in
terms of objects that are איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. Now when you
talk about for example making let's say in נדרים nedarim that I
forbid you to get benefit from me, there the definitions are different.
But if you're talking about objects that are forbidden by הנאה, hana'ah,
we're talking about much more sort of physical practical benefit. So there's
even a question about like the benefit of smell although there the
גמרא gemara says smell is included because that is much more physical.
But it talked about let's say aesthetic or
oral what's the word oral with an A-U but I think anyway
audio, I know, aro, whatever benefit, there that is not biblically prohibited.
So those it really has to be a type of like physical
or monetary benefit. Okay, so the גמרא gemara now goes on. יתיב
רבינא Yativ Ravina וקאמר
לה להאי
שמעתא. vekamar leh l'hai shemu'eta. So Ravina was sitting and telling over
this discussion. אותיב רב רחומי ליה לרבינא. Otiv Rav Rechumi leh l'Ravina.
So Rav Rechumi says to Ravina
who said in the name of רבא Rava that מצוות לאו ליהנות
ניתנו mitzvot lav lehanot nitnu and you fulfill your obligation of covering.
Now I should also add that רבא Rava not only said you
fulfill your obligation but presumably he said you could even use it
לכתחילה. l'chatchila. Okay, so now we're going to look at a teaching
of a ברייתא braitah that seems to contradict this in multiple ways.
שופר של עבודה זרה לא יתקע בו. shofar shel avodah zarah lo
yitka bo. If you have a שופר shofar of עבודה זרה avodah
zarah don't blow it. מאי לאו mai lav and does that not
mean אם תקע לא יצא im taka lo yatza if you did
you did not fulfill your obligation? Because you can't derive benefit from
מצוות. mitzvot. Now of course you could say okay if this is
a contradiction to רבא Rava and it is considered מצוה mitzvah benefit,
why is he assuming like I don't get my fulfill my obligation?
Shouldn't he assume I fulfill my obligation and I transgressed and I
got the forbidden benefit if you consider מצוות mitzvot to be a
source of benefit, a
forbidden benefit? So here the answer is no, we have like a
choice. What should we say happened here? Should we say you fulfilled
the מצוה mitzvah and therefore transgressed and got the benefit of having
used this thing to fulfill the מצוה? mitzvah? Or should we say
you didn't fulfill the מצוה mitzvah and therefore you didn't transgress? So
given the choice I'd rather not fulfill the מצוה mitzvah and not
transgress. So therefore the assumption is that if this is considered to
be forbidden benefit, rather than saying you do the מצוה mitzvah and
transgress, we say you wouldn't fulfill the מצוה. mitzvah. That's the better
of the two options. Okay, so he says here we see you're
not allowed to blow, presumably because it is forbidden in benefit, and
presumably if you blew you would not fulfill the מצוה. mitzvah. So
the גמרא gemara says לא אם תקע יצא. lo im taka yatza.
No, if you did it you would fulfill the מצוה. mitzvah. All
right, here's another ברייתא. braitah. לולב של עבודה זרה לא יטול. lulav
shel avodah zarah lo yitol. Don't take a לולב lulav of עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. מאי לאו mai lav does it not mean אם
נטל לא יצא? im natat lo yatza? If you took it you
did not fulfill your obligation again because it is forbidden in benefit.
לא
אם נטל יצא. lo im natat yatza. No, if you took it
you would fulfill it. והתניא? ve-ha tanya? How could you say that?
Didn't we teach in a ברייתא? braitah? תקע לא יצא נטל לא
יצא. taka lo yatza natat lo yatza. It has the end of
the sentence. If you blew you didn't fulfill your obligation and if
you took your לולב lulav you didn't. So you see רבא's Rava
totally wrong. If you do מצוות mitzvot with these forbidden objects you
do not fulfill your obligation. אמר רב אשי amar Rav Ashi הכי
השתא? hachi hashta? What type of comparison is that? התם hasam
over there שיעורה בעינא. shiura ba'ina. You need a שיעור. shiur. A
לולב lulav has to be a certain size, a שופר shofar has
to be a certain size. עבודה זרה avodah zarah if it is
not just anything of forbidden benefit, that thing is something that was
worshipped as idolatry. What are you supposed to do with things that
are idols? You're supposed to burn them. So therefore כתותי מיכתת שיעוריה.
kitutei mechatat shiurei. The מצוה mitzvah to burn it makes it like
the שיעור shiur is destroyed. Even if you haven't burned it yet.
רש"י Rashi explains this based on the principle of כל העומד לשריפה
כשרוף דמי. kol ha'omed lisreifah kesaruf dami. If it's supposed to be
burnt it's like it's already burnt. You don't have to go that
far. You could also just say that part of the point of
a שיעור shiur is not just the quantitative size but the idea
that it has to be something of significance. So something that is
supposed to be destroyed undermines any sense of significance of the object.
So when you have a שופר shofar or לולב lulav עבודה זרה
avodah zarah it has nothing to do with the איסור הנאה. issur
hana'ah. It has to do with the fact that it's supposed to
be destroyed and therefore it undermines the significance and you can't use
it as a מצוה mitzvah object.
הכא, hacha, one minute, הכא hacha
here we're talking about using ashes of עפר ועפר תיכתש afar ve-afar
tichtas for covering the blood. So כל מה דמיכתת מעלי לכיסוי. kol
mah de-mechatat malei le-chisui. The more it would be burned the better
it would be able to be used for covering the blood. So
here there's no problem that it's standing to be burned and said
in another way, even if it's not like we imagine it as
already burned. But here, right, we have a different way we think
about לולב lulav and שופר shofar as a מצוה mitzvah object, right,
as a תשמישי מצוה. tashmishei mitzvah. We don't think about the dirt
that you use to cover the blood as the same type of
a way as a מצוה mitzvah object, right, so you know. Let's
say for example, I mean, it'd be manure, there are laws about,
you know, how do you dispose of מצוה mitzvah objects. You wouldn't
say that you have those questions by the stuff you're using to
cover. So therefore, because there's no שיעור shiur and there's no significance
that we have to give the object, there's not a problem that
it's standing to be burnt. So that's why there you do not
and here you do, it has nothing to do with the prohibition
of deriving benefit. The question the גמרא Gemara itself has not addressed
that רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot address is okay, but even if
that's true, there at least it says לכתחילה l'chatchila
not to take it, right? Here, meaning even in the גמרא's Gemara's
initial response for example, when it said that it was not as
if it's burnt up or whatever, it still has said don't do
it לכתחילה. l'chatchila. Here it was never bothered with לכתחילה. l'chatchila. Now
again, you could say, okay, but at the end we see that
the issue is that there's because it's burnt up and there's not
a שיעור shiur and here it is and here you know and
that's the difference. But another point that רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
do make is the and this is interesting because it goes back
to the גמרא Gemara about about not to kick the dirt over
because it's not to show that the מצות mitzvot are בזויות עליו,
bizuyot alav, that they say there might be some scenarios where because
something was used in עבודה זרה avodah zarah and so on, whether
it's now עבודה זרה avodah zarah or not, that it's considered to
be a בזיון bizayon to use that object for a מצוה. mitzvah.
So even if for example you could have a case of a
שופר shofar that let's say was once עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, even
if now it's you know the גוי goy is מבטל mevattel it
and it's not forbidden or whatever, לכתחילה l'chatchila you shouldn't use it
because it's not appropriate to use something that was once worshipped even
forgetting that it's no longer that case for a מצוה. mitzvah. But
that they say would not be the case by covering the blood
because although you're not supposed to treat the מצוה mitzvah in a
disparaging way, you're not supposed to kick the whatever so you like
this מצוה mitzvah is a meaningless מצוה mitzvah in terms of the
מצוה, mitzvah, but in terms of the object, there's no need to
have give to treat you know that the object of the מצוה,
mitzvah, which could be dirt and could be excrement and could be
other types of things, there's no need to say that the you
know that there has to be a certain respect the מצוה mitzvah
object has to be a respectful object. So the same it could
be dirt and excrement, it could be an object that was once
used in עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So those are two differences. We
are now saying that according to רבא, Rava, מצות לאו להנות ניתנו,
mitzvot lav lehenot nitnu, so something that's אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah you
could use for a מצוה. mitzvah. What about these cases about שופר
shofar and לולב lulav etc.? That's not because it was forbidden in
benefit, that's because it was actually it was an alive עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, it had to be destroyed and therefore that undermined its
significance whereas by the מצ by the object of the dirt and
that you cover the blood with, there's no שיעור, there's no quantitative
size, there's no need of significance and therefore even if it's supposed
to be destroyed it can still be used and what I added
related to that is there would also be no question about like
like is it tainted because it was once used in עבודה זרה?
avodah zarah? There the object doesn't have to have significance. You have
to treat the מצוה mitzvah with respect, but the object does not
have to have any sort of you know respect any significance to
it and any status. It's Jolyn then Michael, yeah.
Yeah, so that's actually I can see a practical application of that
today is that we there are occasions where we turn churches into
synagogues.
I was going
to say that.
Yeah. Yeah and can we use anything in the building?
Yeah, so those are there's a lot of הלכה halakhah about that
because you're really not supposed to and it happens all the happens
all the time for obvious reasons because you know they're
better than the other direction. That's true. ארון קודש. aron kodesh. Yeah,
that's what I would have.
I understand.
Okay, so that there's whole discussions about that and God willing when
we get to מגילה Megillah where this comes up in the third
פרק, perek, so that's not so far away, that's only two years
away, so we'll discuss it then. Yes. That was your question? Okay.
No no but I have a couple of other comments. You know
one is you can only take this whole thing of עומד לשרוף
כשרוף דמי omeid l'isoreif k'saruf dami and so on so far because
otherwise
if you really say that and it shouldn't be אסור assur to
use you know shouldn't be אסור assur to begin with, which is
why anyway I didn't yeah okay fine. But in the other one
was I want to make sure I understood what you were saying.
So you're saying it's not a problem saying it's מצות בזויות mitzvot
bizuyot because let's say they worshiped נידחת, nidachah, let's say the עבודה
זרה avodah zarah was worshipping the ground. So would you then say
that you shouldn't use the ground for כיסוי הדם?
kisui hadam? No. No, that is what I am saying that רש"י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafot basically say that it is not a problem
to use dirt that was worshipped for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. You
don't have the even a question about like it's not appropriate to
use such objects for a מצוה mitzvah because again there the dirt
is not really a מצוה mitzvah object. So even though you are
doing a מצוה, mitzvah, the dirt is not a מצוה mitzvah object.
There's no problem of בזויות עליו bizuyot alav because right
yeah okay so now we start the next פרק, perek, so that
is the end of covering the blood. Now that the blood is
covered we're finally getting pretty close and you didn't שחט אותו ואת
בנו, shecht oto ve'et bno, right? First you had to make sure
you did the שחיטה shechitah correctly, then you had to check for
טריפות, tereifot, then you had to make sure also you had to
figure out whether there was a fetus in the womb, then you
had after you've checked for טריפות tereifot now you have to make
a little bit before you שחט shechted for טריפות tereifot too maybe
it could have been conceptually earlier but anyway it was packaged with
the שחיטה. shechitah. Now that the you have to make sure or
maybe you did one שחיטה, shechitah, you שחט shechted it and it
wasn't טרף, treif, now don't go ahead and שחט shecht the בנו
bno on the same day, that was the previous פרק, perek, don't
do that. Now that you've שחט shechted it, covered the blood if
it was a חיה chayah or עוף, of, not if it was
a בהמה, behemah, now getting closer to being ready to eat it
but wait don't eat the גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. And after the
גיד הנשה gid hanasheh then we're going to get to the בשר
בחלב. basar bechalav. Interestingly, there is no פרק perek directly about... about
removing or even משניות mishnayos directly about removing the blood or removing
the חלב, chelev, which is quite fascinating. You'd think that those would
be pretty front and center. It could be that the חלב chelev
is very obvious. There's not a big deal in, you know, it
just sort of sits there mostly and whatever, but still removing the
blood isn't an obvious process. So it is it is curious, but
anyway we now turn to גיד הנשה gid hanasheh and we are
really getting very close into, you know, the the heavy kashrus discussions.
So let's take a look. גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, the the sinew
which is, you know, in the calf, in the thigh, נוהג בארץ
ובחוצה לארץ, noheig ba'aretz uv'chutz la'aretz, applies in the Land of Israel
and outside the Land of Israel obviously, בפני הבית ושלא בפני הבית
bifnei habayis v'shelo bifnei habayis in the presence of the temple or
not. Again, this is the structure that we keep on repeating. There
be cases later on that not all these things are true, for
here it's pretty obvious. בחולין ובמוקדשים, bechullin uv'mukdashim, tomorrow God willing. Anyway,
okay, start a picture book. Okay, let's finish the mishnah and Joel
shows the picture. Whether it is non-sanctified or sanctified animals or or
sacrifices. ונוהג ב... v'noheig b... now that means that if you're a
כהן kohen and you're eating a חטאת chatas or you're a ישראל
yisrael and you're eating a שלמים, shlamim, don't eat the גיד הנשה.
gid hanasheh. There is an interesting question about
an עולה. olah.
Do you have to not burn the עולה olah on the on
the בית ה... beisa... you know, on the מזבח? mizbeach? Is it
somehow, you know, forbidden to be put? But you burn the חלב
chelev and the דם dam or whatever. So what is the status
of the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh by an עולה? olah? We will
discuss. But anyway,
the other question I should take not really whether you burn it
on the altar, but since an עולה olah is forbidden to be
eaten, does that does you know, how does the fact that you
have two prohibitions there? I mean a חטאת chatas and a שלמים
shlamim you can eat, just don't eat the גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh.
Is the fact that the whole עולה olah is forbidden to be
eaten, is there a double prohibition relating to the גיד הנשה? gid
hanasheh?
So what if you ate the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh of an
עולה?
olah? Yeah. So that'll be discussed in the גמרא. gemara. But generally
it applies to קרבנות, korbanos, certainly קרבנות korbanos you can eat. ונוהג
בבהמה ובחיה, v'noheig bivhemah uvchayah, it applies to domesticated and non-domesticated animals.
It's never limited. It just says לא יאכלו בני ישראל את גיד
הנשה. lo yochlu bnei yisrael es gid hanasheh. בירך הימין ובירך השמאל,
beyerech hayamin uveyerech hasmol, the right and the left side. That will
be debated. Some say only the right side. ואינו נוהג בעוף, v'eino
noheig be'oph, it does not apply by bird. מפני שאין לו כף
mipnei she'ein lo kaph because although a bird, although he has that
sinew, it does not have אשר כף הירך, asher kaph hayerech, which
is unlike the כף kaph is like the hand, but you know,
it's like the rounded part of the thigh. So birds don't have,
you know, sort of the same type of rounded thigh the same
way animals and humans do. Again, if there was a picture I
would show you, I'll show you tomorrow. Maybe Joel will show us
in a minute. ונוהג בשליל, v'noheig b'shalil, it applies to the fetus.
רבי יהודה אומר אינו נוהג בשליל, Rabbi Yehudah omer eino noheig b'shalil,
it does not. And that presumably is a debate about the nine-month-old
fetus where again, this תנא קמא tanna kamma here seems to be
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, who says the nine-month-old fetus has its independent
status. So therefore its גיד הנשה gid hanasheh is a גיד הנשה
gid hanasheh of a separate animal, whereas רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says
no, the fetus even nine months old is part of the mother
and therefore it's not a גיד הנשה gid hanasheh because it's not
it's not considered an animal yet, it's just considered a part of
the mother. וחלבן מותר, vechelban mutar, the fat is permissible. Which fat?
Does it mean the fat of a שליל, shalil, so we're back
into שליל shalil world, or it might mean the fat of the
גיד הנשה? gid hanasheh? There is fat that surrounds the גיד, gid,
is that considered forbidden fat or not? We'll discuss that in the
גמרא. gemara. ואין הטבחים נאמנים על גיד הנשה, v'ein hatavachim ne'emanim al
gid hanasheh, butchers cannot be trusted to say they removed the גיד
הנשה. gid hanasheh. Yeah, don't worry about it, I took care of
it. Okay, why? Because it is a very difficult thing to do
and therefore, you see that's an interesting point. The assumption here normally
is that you don't need השגחה, hashgachah, you don't need a הכשר,
hechsher, right? If a normal Jew tells you, a halachically abiding Jew
tells you, "Yes, I took care of everything," then the principle is
עד אחד נאמן באיסורין, ed echad ne'eman b'isurin, you can trust somebody
about kashrus matters. Interestingly, even if they have a monetary vested interest
in it, you don't need השגחה hashgachah from... well, technically speaking you
can trust the person. Of course, we're not getting into, you know,
then became a whole question. I mean obviously, you know, for some,
you know, first of all the יצר הרע yeitzer hara can be
very strong and number number one, and you see that in the
גמרא, gemara, the question about even though technically עד אחד נאמן באיסורין,
ed echad ne'eman b'isurin, sometimes the יצר הרע yeitzer hara is too
strong and we really can't trust people.
So here was a case which
was about trusting people to have removed the גיד הנשה.
gid hanasheh. That is so difficult and so time-consuming that you cannot,
even though normally you trust somebody about kashrus, even the person selling
you the meat, you don't trust them here. Is this the kind
of thing that you would know if you're eating it? Well, presumably
presumably not, meaning presumably, especially if
you cut it up
to pieces of the meat, you know, after it's
sliced up,
you
wouldn't be able to tell, right.
Or or and that's the point, you can't trust them.
Maybe you have
to inspect it.
It doesn't mean necessarily
has to
supervise,
maybe it just means you have to inspect if you know a
way to inspect it after the fact. Okay, don't don't buy hamburger
meat. You're saying just don't buy, like you know, just buy like
the breast or whatever you know doesn't have the גיד הנשה. gid
hanasheh. Right, or inspect it, or supervise. דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi
Meir, that's what Rabbi Meir says. וחכמים אומרים נאמנים עליו ועל החלב.
vachachamim omrim ne'emanim alav v'al hachelev. No, they are trusted to say
they removed the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh and they're trusted to say
they removed the fat. So here at least you're getting a reference
to the fact that the fat had to be removed although it
is not the focus of the discussion. Joe, you have a picture
there, the גיד הנשה? Gid Hanasheh? Can we take a look? Ah,
here we go. Very nice, gorgeous. Okay, so. Anyway, here we have
right the גיד הנשה, Gid Hanasheh, this long sinew that goes all
the way down here. Okay? So anyway, so this is and this
is the כף הירך, Kaf Hayarech, right, because it's sort of you
see that it's sort of like it's the כף הירך. Kaf Hayarech.
Yeah. I mean it's pointing to this part which is this thick
muscle. Coming in here, that's not the כף הירך Kaf Hayarech anymore?
No, this is not the same sinew. Oh, I don't know, that.
Oh, no, that's גיד החיצון. Gid Hachitzon. We'll talk about this. This
is a discussion as it comes to the גמרא. Gemara. It starts
here, it branches off here. Oh, yeah, anyway, nobody's looking anyway. Anyway,
it starts here, it's very, very long. It has also all of
these, what makes it hard to remove, it has all of these
tributaries or whatever they're called, right, all of these extended parts, and
then it has this other whole branch, which we'll talk about. So
you can see why it's a lot of work to remove it.
You can't eat any of that. Right, it's a sinew, not a
nerve. Muscles. No, it says here nerves. Sciatic nerve? Sciatic nerve? Is
it really a nerve? Gid means a sinew, but it might be
a nerve. I mean, nerves are sheathed, so maybe it is. Okay,
maybe. But so the משנה Mishnah turns now to מוקדשים, Mukdashim, and
birds don't have a כף. kaf. You can't eat, you can eat
the meat, you can't eat the גיד. gid. No, but you can't
eat any of the tributaries and even the parts not on the
כף. kaf. Right, why? Those are the קנוקנות. kenoknaot. We'll discuss it
in the גמרא. Gemara. Those are the קנוקנות. kenoknaot. That's the sciatic
nerve. גיד הנשה. Gid Hanasheh. Yeah, that's what it says. Sciatic nerve.
People who have sciatica, that means they have a problem with their
גיד הנשה. Gid Hanasheh. Yeah, there you go. So יעקב אבינו Yaakov
Avinu had sciatica. All right. Let's keep moving. We will have plenty
of opportunity for those who like the anatomy to discuss that as
we continue. Let's start in the גמרא. Gemara. מוקדשים Mukdashim is applied
to sacrifices. פשיטא, Peshita, of course. משום דאקדשיה פקע ליה איסור גיד
מיניה? mishum de'akdeshei paka lei issur gid minei? You sanctify this animal,
so a minute ago this animal was חולין chulin and you couldn't
eat the גיד הנשה. Gid Hanasheh. If you would have שחטed shecht
it, you could eat the meat but not the גיד הנשה. Gid
Hanasheh. Now you make it into a קרבן. korban. So we, what,
you think the prohibition of גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh disappeared? Of course
it applies to קרבנות. korbanot. Just because you sanctified it, what does
that do to the prohibition? Of course it's still the same. So
תוספות Tosafot says, the problem is that there's not a חידוש chiddush
in any of the patterns. So we think, we assume that there's
got to be a חידוש chiddush in one of them that's got
to be in the מוקדשים.
mukdashim. וכי תימא, vechi teima, lest you say, יש בגידין בנותן טעם,
yesh begidin benoten taam, maybe you'll say that גידים, gidim, now this
is a major question throughout the פרק. perek. Is there any taste
in the גיד הנשה? Gid Hanasheh? Why do I care? It's forbidden
regardless. I care, number one, if I cook the גיד gid with
the meat, can I remove the גיד gid afterwards and eat the
meat? Or am I concerned that the גיד gid gave off taste?
Like if I cooked it with the חלב, cheilev, obviously I could
eat it after. That's one classic example. The other relevant issue is,
if the תורה Torah forbids גיד gid whether it has taste or
not. So let's say this animal is also a קרבן. korban. So
is the גיד gid also forbidden because it is sanctified and it's
part of a קרבן? korban? And when I, so if it has
taste, then when I eat the גיד, gid, I got benefit, I
got benefit from the קרבן, korban, I transgressed from that prohibition. If
it didn't have taste, so I didn't really
get benefit, like if I eat the, let's say I eat the
horn of
a
קרבן korban or the hoof of a קרבן.
korban. So I'm a little crazy and I
put קדשים kodashim
in my mouth, but I didn't
actually transgress benefiting from it.
So if the גיד gid has taste or not will determine whether
I transgress if I eat the גיד gid of a קרבן korban
for the prohibition
of קרבנות, korbanot, not the prohibition of גיד. gid. So let's take
gelatin, no problem. What's it made from? Like if you ground the
hoof and make it a gel and then you would derive benefit.
וכי תימא יש בגידין בנותן טעם, vechi teima yesh begidin benoten taam,
the גידים gidim have taste and because of that ואתי איסור מוקדשים
וחייל אאיסור גיד, ve'ati issur mukdashim vechayal a'issur gid, and therefore what
it's telling you is not that you transgress גיד gid by a
קרבן, korban, but that you transgress a קרבן korban prohibition by a
גיד. gid. Meaning, if I made my animal into a קרבן korban
and I eat the גיד, gid, not only do I transgress the
prohibition of גיד הנשה, Gid Hanasheh, I also transgress the prohibition of
benefiting from a קרבן korban because there's taste to the גיד. gid.
If that's what the משנה Mishnah is telling me, האי מוקדשים נוהג
בגיד מיבעי ליה. hai mukdashim noheig begid miba'ei lei. It shouldn't have
said the prohibition of גיד gid applies to a קרבן. korban. It
should have said the prohibition of קרבנות korbanot applies even to the
גיד. gid. If I sanctify the animal, the קרבן korban prohibition applies
to the גיד. gid. That's what it should have said. אלא, ella,
that can't be the רישא, reisha, קסבר אין בגידין בנותן טעם. kasavar
ein begidin benoten taam. Maybe we'll try it this way. There isn't
taste to the גיד gid and therefore it's not אסור assur when
it's part of a קרבן korban as a קרבן, korban, it's אסור
assur as a גיד. gid. ובמוקדשים איסור גיד איכא איסור מוקדשים ליכא.
uvemukdashim issur gid ika issur mukdashim leika. There's only the prohibition of
גיד, gid, not the prohibition of a קרבן. korban. So the way
to read the משנה Mishnah is גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh applies to
קרבנות, korbanot, the way to read it means גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh
is the only, meaning a גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh in a קרבן,
korban, the only prohibition for the גיד gid is the prohibition of
גיד הנשה. Gid Hanasheh. It is not prohibited also because of the
prohibition of קרבנות. korbanot. It is only the prohibition of גיד gid
because the prohibition of קרבנות korbanot does not apply to it because
there is no benefit from eating the גיד. gid. So איסור גיד
איכא איסור מוקדשים ליכא. issur gid ika issur mukdashim leika. That's one
way to read the משנה. Mishnah. So now the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, וסבר תנא דידן אין בגידין בנותן טעם? vesavar tanna didan
ein begidin benoten taam? Is that really what the תנא Tanna thinks?
True that our תנא Tanna could hold that a גיד Gid has
no taste? And again, the reason we're making this argument is to
say that it's only the prohibition of גיד Gid and not the
prohibition of a קרבן. Korban. והתנן, Vehasnan, we taught in the coming
משנה Mishnah and we assume that it is the same voice, it's
the same author, ירך שנתבשל בה גיד
הנשה,
Yerech shenitbashel
bah gid
hanasheh, if you cooked the thigh of the animal with the גיד
הנשה, Gid Hanasheh, אם יש בה בנותן טעם הרי זו אסורה, im
yesh bah benoten taam harei zo asurah, if there is taste of
the גיד Gid in the if it gives off its taste, meaning
like it's a standard question, how much of the איסור Issur was
within the pot versus how much of the היתר? Heter? And was
there enough היתר Heter to outweigh the איסור Issur so there's no
taste? So that's the question the משנה Mishnah asks. If there was
enough היתר Heter that the taste was nullified, it's okay. If however
there was not enough of the meat and there was too much
of the גיד Gid and it gave off taste, then it's forbidden.
So you see we're assuming that the גיד Gid does give off
taste. So הרי זו אסורה. Harei zo asurah. So there it says
that you won't be able to eat the thigh if the גיד,
Gid, if there was not enough meat and the גיד Gid gave
off taste. So you see we assume the גיד Gid gives off
taste. So we now don't have a way to read the משנה.
Mishnah. Number one, because we assume that the גיד Gid gives off
taste, it's obviously אסור Assur also as a קרבן, Korban, not just
as a גיד, Gid, but if you sanctified it also as a
קרבן. Korban. So what's the חידוש? Chiddush? Of course it's אסור Assur
as a גיד, Gid, and if you wanted to tell me a
חידוש Chiddush that it's also אסור Assur as a קרבן, Korban, say
that, say a גיד, Gid, say the prohibition of קרבן Korban applies
to a גיד. Gid. Don't tell me that the prohibition of גיד
Gid applies, that's obvious. The גמרא Gemara says אלא הכא בולדות קדשים
עסקינן. Ela hacha bivladot kodashim askinan. Okay, here's the scenario. We're talking
not that you sanctified an animal that was already grown, the mother
was a קרבן, Korban, and then the mother became pregnant and gave
birth to a calf. דקסבר נוהג בשליל, Dekasavar noheg bashalil, we'll assume
גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh applies to the fetus. And therefore דקסבר ולדות
קדשים במי אימן הן קדושים, Dekasavar vladot kodashim bimei iman hen kedoshim,
when a cow gets pregnant, a cow that's a קרבן Korban gets
pregnant, the fetus from the moment it begins to be formed in
the mother's womb is already sanctified. The sanctity of the mother extends
to the fetus from the moment the fetus begins to grow. So
in that scenario, that scenario and we're saying the prohibition of גיד
הנשה Gid Hanasheh applies from the moment it begins to be a
fetus. So in that scenario, דאיסור גיד ואיסור מוקדשין בהדי הדדי קאתי,
Deissur gid veissur mukdashin bahadi hadadi kaati, they both come at the
same time. So the question was, what is the חידוש Chiddush that
the prohibition of גיד Gid applies to קרבנות? Korbanot? So I might
have if the prohibition of גיד Gid came first, of course it's
going to remain. So the answer is, the prohibition of גיד Gid
does not always come first. If we're talking about a fetus that
is growing in a קרבן, Korban, okay, the mother was a קרבן
Korban and then it wasn't brought yet, it was sanctified and then
the fetus is growing. In that case the prohibition of גיד Gid
did not come first. At the same moment it became prohibited as
a גיד, Gid, this fetus, and prohibited as a קרבן. Korban. And
in that case I might have said, because there are two, maybe
they're competing against one another, maybe it would only be the קרבן
Korban prohibition not the גיד, Gid, so it tells you no, even
though it's a קרבן Korban and they're coming at the same time,
the prohibition of גיד Gid applies as well. Both are the answer.
Why? Because that's not what we're talking about. Because why don't you
assume that we hold that the fetus is prohibited, what if also
part of the גיד Gid was allowed in a fetus and the
prohibition came later? You're right, actually that would even make for a
better חידוש, Chiddush, that it started as a קרבן Korban and then
the prohibition of גיד Gid came and then
you're right. So actually we're going to get there. That actually does
make things even a nicer way of saying it. Until now the
claim you're saying is absolutely correct and we'll discuss that, but until
now the problem had been the order. גיד, Gid, if an animal
starts with the prohibition of גיד, Gid,
then you make it a קרבן. Korban. So the question is of
course the prohibition of גיד Gid is there, it started there, it's
going to remain there. So we're now describing a scenario where they
both came at the same time. When it began being a fetus,
both of them came and therefore you know it's a חידוש Chiddush
that they both still apply. James is saying the bigger חידוש Chiddush
is actually if the order is reversed. First it's a קרבן Korban
and then it's a גיד Gid and maybe that will work if
the prohibition of גיד Gid comes after, it's not when it's not
a fetus.
And even though it's
not allowed, isn't it only eight months?
That's a very good point, I'm going to get back to that.
Okay, so let's first so James raises two excellent questions. Let's see
where the גמרא Gemara goes with this. So the גמרא Gemara says
ומי מצית מוקמת לה בשליל, Umi mazzat mokmat lah bishalil, how can
you say it's talking about a fetus? דהא מדקתני סיפא, Deha midkatni
seifa, the end it says נוהג בשליל, noheg bashalil, right? The end
of this משנה Mishnah says oh and it applies to a fetus,
and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says it doesn't apply to a fetus,
מכלל דרישא לאו בשליל עסקינן, micklal dersha lav bishalil askinan, the implication
is that the first taste of a קרבן Korban was not talking
yet about a fetus. Fetus was introduced at the end. So the
גמרא Gemara says הכי קאמר, hachi kaamar, this is what it means
to say. דבר זה, Davar zeh, although we've been talking about a
קרבן Korban and that it's a fetus and so on, you should
be aware that דבר זה מחלוקת רב יהודה ורבנן davar zeh machloket
Rav Yehuda veRabbanan is really debated, that we've been assuming the משנה
Mishnah saying that we're talking about a קרבן Korban that was a
fetus and we're assuming that גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh applies to a
שליל, shalil, but be aware that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda disagrees. So
at this stage we're saying that we're talking about a... A fetus
of a קרבן korban and it becomes prohibited as a גיד gid
and as a קרבן korban at the same moment, and גיד's gid
and James's question, which is it's even a bigger חידוש chiddush if
the prohibition of קרבן korban came first, is a very good one.
We'll get back to it. And but that's what we're assuming right
now. Came at the same moment, and that's the scenario of גיד
gid by a קרבן. korban. But the גמרא Gemara is not done.
The גמרא Gemara says like this: ומי מצית אמרת דשוויי בהדי הדדי
קאתו? U'mi matzes amart d'shavai b'hadai hadadi ka'asu? And how can you
say they come at the same time? והתנן, Ve'hasnan, we taught in
the משנה: Mishna: על אלו טומאתן נזיר מגלח, Al elu tumasan nazir
megalayach, on the following טומאות tumos a נזיר nazir will shave. Because
meaning a נזיר nazir if he becomes טמא tamei he has to
shave his hair and start again. Now that's only if he becomes
טמא tamei to a corpse, not the other thing. And even if
he becomes טמא tamei to a corpse, it's only a certain type
of טומאה tumah of a corpse that's considered to represent the primary
corpse itself, not some type of a derivative טומאה. tumah. Okay, and
therefore there's a list of things. So here's the list: על המת,
Al hames, if he touches a whole corpse, ועל כזית מן המת,
ve'al kezayis min hames, or if he touches a כזית kezayis of
the corpse. And then it goes on and there's a lot of
other things on the list. וקשיא לן, Vekashis lan, and we ask
the question, על כזית מן המת מגלח על כולו לא כל שכן?
al kezayis min hames megalayach, al kulo lo kol sheken? If you
become טמא, tamei, if you have to shave for a start your
נזירות nezirus again for a כזית kezayis worth of the corpse, of
course you have to do it for the whole corpse. So why
did it mention the whole corpse? Just say a כזית kezayis and
of course if the whole corpse, it has many, many, it's much,
much bigger than that. ואמר רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan, so Rabbi
Yochanan explains, no, here's why you have to say a corpse even
if,
because you can have a time where you can have a corpse
that isn't the size of a כזית. kezayis. How can you have
a corpse that isn't the size of a כזית? kezayis? We have
these things like, you know, the mother expels miscarried, לא נצרכה אלא
לנפל, Lo nitzrecha ela lenefel, it's a very early term miscarriage, שלא
נקראו איבריו בגידים, she'lo nikre'u evarav begidin, and the limbs have still
not been sort of, you know, tied with its sinews. Meaning, it's
just his way of saying that it's a very tiny, tiny thing
and therefore could even be smaller than a כזית. kezayis. So you
could even have a corpse of a very early term miscarriage that's
smaller than a כזית kezayis worth. What's relevant for us is that
he says that at the early stages the גיד gid doesn't exist
yet. Which is, right. So which is therefore he's saying, so therefore
the order is actually the order that James was saying. If it
becomes sanctified in its mother's womb, it becomes a קרבן korban sanctity
from the minute it begins to be forming, but the גיד הנשה
Gid HaNasheh prohibition only comes later. Okay, now the question is so
what? Maybe that's exactly the case of the משנה. Mishna. That would
make a nice case. The גיד הנשה Gid HaNasheh came later because,
you know, because it was a fetus. First it was אסור assur
as a קרבן, korban, then it had its גיד. gid. And now
tell me that the prohibition of גיד gid still applies even though
it comes later. So let's read the next line of the גמרא:
Gemara: אלמא איסור גיד ואיסור מקדשים קודם. Alma issur gid ve'issur mikdashim
kodem. So you see that the איסור issur of הקדש hekdesh comes
first. So they don't come at the same time. So the problem
of the גמרא Gemara is not that there wouldn't be a nice
חידוש chiddush of the משנה, Mishna, but that the גמרא Gemara isn't
sure that it's true. Maybe if the גיד gid comes later, maybe
it can't apply to a קרבן korban because of the principle of
אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal al issur. Right? So
if it's already אסור assur as a קרבן korban and they're not
coming at the exact same time, maybe now that it gets its
גיד, gid, maybe that won't be forbidden as a גיד gid because
it's already forbidden as a קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara says
no: אף על גב דאיסור מקדשים קודם אתי איסור גיד חייל עלייהו.
Af al gav de'issur mikdashim kodem, asi issur gid chail alaihu. Even
though the prohibition of קרבן korban comes first, the prohibition of גיד
gid comes and takes place upon it. שכן, Sheken, why can it
even though the איסור issur of קרבן korban is weightier and comes
first? שכן איסורו נוהג בבני נח. Sheken issuro noheg bivnei Noach. It
has a weightiness that you don't have by קרבנות, korbanos, that it
was prohibited to non-Jews. Now that doesn't really mean it. גיד gid
is not prohibited to non-Jews. It means it was prohibited to us
when we were still non-Jewish. It was prohibited before מתן תורה. Matan
Torah. And because of that, that gives it a certain type of
a weight that means that even though it comes later, it will
still apply. So we'll talk more about that tomorrow. I just want
to wrap up by saying two things. Where the גמרא Gemara is
right now is where James wanted us to get, although in a
different way, where it says that you have this fetus, first it's
a קרבן, korban, then the prohibition of גיד gid comes about. And
the, that's what the משנה Mishna is saying, that even when the
prohibition of גיד gid comes later, it still applies to קרבנות. korbanos.
Why don't we say אין איסור חל על איסור? ein issur chal
al issur? And the answer is because the prohibition of גיד gid
has a certain weightiness that allows it to apply even if the
animal is already forbidden as a קרבן. korban. Right? So I'll talk
about that more tomorrow, but I did want to say one important
point that James raises, which תוספות Tosafot also raises, which is what
does it mean when it says that the prohibition of גיד gid
applies when this animal is a fetus? I mean, it goes all
the way back at, certainly thought day one, but now at least
whatever, in its first few weeks, as soon as it gets the
גיד. gid. We had assumed that when there was a prohibition of
גיד הנשה, Gid HaNasheh, right, that when you שחט shacht the mother,
everybody agrees that the גיד gid is permissible unless until the fetus
is maybe nine months old. But less than nine months, it's considered
a part of the mother and there's no prohibition of גיד הנשה.
Gid HaNasheh. That seemed to be universal, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and so on. So that's a great question. תוספות
Tosafot asks the question, and תוספות Tosafot basically says it depends whether
you שחט shachted the mother. If you שחט shacht the mother, then
we view this fetus as, you know, as a part of the
mother. If the mother wasn't שחט shachted and either it miscarried and
the fetus came out, or you stuck your hand in and removed
the fetus, or the fetus got born nine months later, then since
the mother was never שחט shachted when the fetus was in it,
it never gets got defined as being a part of the mother,
and then we can look backwards and say that the prohibition of
גיד gid began from the very beginning when it began to become
a when it was a fetus. So this is another twist on
that idea of the independence and dependence of the fetus on the
mother, that maybe when you שחט shecht the mother it's a limb,
but when you don't שחט shecht the mother and it winds up
getting born, then we always have viewed it as having been independent.
Okay.